Hello friends, so in this video we will
see Top 10 Health Insurance Companies
in India for the year 2025, 2026.  The
data we have collected for this video is the
latest.  The reports published
by IRDAI and CIO in February 2026.
Now just
in February 2026, we are going to talk about that data
and see which are the
top 10 health insurance companies of India.  Now let us
start with a news that I
read and after reading it I was quite shocked
because my own health
insurance is currently from Star Health Insurance.
Now look at this news which says
Top 10 Insurers with Highest Number of
Complaints in Handling Health Insurance
Star Care and Niva among top three.  Now
see how he has said this in the news.
I'll do a little highlighting.  Search
in policy holder dissatisfaction.  Star
Health tops the list with more than 12,000
complaints recorded in FY2025. Care
Health and Niwapa are far behind
receiving significant backlash.  Now
after reading this method, I was a
little shocked because I myself am a
star health person.  So I was scared that there were
12,000 complaints.  Oh my God, I should
shift from Star Health to some other
insurance.  But I think I am an engineer.
So I always keep an eye on the data every year to see
which company
is performing and how.  So I think that
responsible journalism is something that should be done in
ethical, independent data analysis
and in public interest.  This has
reduced a bit these days.  So
people get scared after reading all this that brother,
this has become a much bigger issue than 12,000 complaints.
So when we break this down,
we will see
how many health insurance complaints out of 12,000 have been
made by that company, it is very important to see that.
So what I mean is that if
we break down the percentage, the total
complaints
are 12186 and Life Assured Star Health has done
2.38 crores.  So if seen in percentage,
it just happens.
Care Health has insured 2.55 crore
lives and if we look at their complaint
percentage, it is only 2% and that
of Nivea Bhupa is only 33%.
Why did I mention these three companies?
Because in this news,
they have mentioned these three companies as top
three.  So after reading this, I feel a
little nervous.  So keep in
mind that you don't have to go by figures.  If you
say 12,000, it
seems like a huge amount individually.  But brother, Star Health
is such a big company that it is
insuring people worth crores.  Out of that,
12,000 comes to 5%.02% percentage wise.
So for this, do
not trust such news and see, it is very important to see how I always
simplify the data and
present it to you.
So first let us see that
they have said that there are so many complaints,
so let us see the data of these complaints.
Look, 12000 complaints are shown here.
Here almost 4000, here 4000, so these
complaints are the overall data, which is the
data coming from our CIO report.
So it's a bit of a panic just looking at the figures.
So
what will we do?  We will break it down and
say that there are 1 lakh policy holders on complaints.
What happens now?  Now this
quantum becomes a little bit justifiable.
So if 1 lakh people take
health insurance, then complaints from 51 people
come to the CIO for Star Health.  It is
18 and it is 17.  So look at the figures now,
when we look at lakhs, it has reduced drastically.
And as I said,
if we look at it percentage wise, it is only 5%.  So it
is very important to see the percentile.  So
I just wanted to show this on this chart.  Now let's
come to what I have consolidated.
So in the last three years, I have been posting videos
every year on health insurance, which health
insurance company is good.  From that, I have
consolidated the questions asked by thousands of people after each video and have done
two-three things this time.  One is from where
I have taken this reference.  I have put the links of the
reports of IRDIA and the CIO
in the description of the video.
So what do you do?  The link has to be
clicked.  Download the PDF of the report
and view it comfortably.
I have also told you where to look.  Look,
I have inserted a table here.  Let me show you.
Look, here I have put a table in which
I have written
which chart to see in which report.
So that will be very
helpful to you.  Now let's come to our
consolidated chart. As usual, I
simplify things.  You know
I used to work in research and development.
So I have a habit of explaining things to people easily
and I also make the selection process
easy.  So
these four companies shown in blue color are
specialist health insurance, to be
precise they do
stand-alone insurance only for
health, so their focus is clear only on
health insurance, these two
companies HDFC and ICICI LBA HDFCO are
general insurance companies.  So if it is not just health, the
insurance covers the rest as well.
And the companies below are all
public sector companies.  I have
included this specifically this time
because in many previous videos people had asked
me to recommend public sector companies also.  So,
according to me, all these top 10 companies are good.
If you look at their ratio, then the number of
complaints per lakh is very less for all the people.
Some people have like two complaints
per lakh which is very good in fact.  But
you should keep a little bit of attention in the public sector.
What happens here is that many
times the big company schemes,
government schemes or
group insurance of big companies are
included in this, so many
complaints are resolved by the HR of the companies, so they do
not surface out for this, so
anyway if you have to go to public sector
companies then United
India Insurance is the best
because if you look at them, there is only one
complaint in a lakh, their percentage of claims
settled in last 3 months is 95% which is
good ok and their incurred claims to
claims ratio is also very big.  So
this is also a very good thing.  So if you want to
go to the public sector then you
can go to this company.  If we talk about
general insurance, then there
are two general insurance companies, HDFC Air and ICICI LBARD, out of which
I like ICICI LBRD a little bit
because their claim settlement
within 3 months is 98.45%.
His insured lives
appear to be 4.09 crore.  But as I
said earlier, groups are included in it.
So for this, I have greyed it
out a little in both the cases because
if the group is included then there is a little bit of
misleading in understanding oneself.
But yes this is also a big
company.  So you can also go to such a Lombard.
Their claim settlement ratio is also
quite good.  And within 3 months
they have settled the claims of 98.45% people.
Now let us come to the private
sector which focuses only on health.
These four companies are known to everyone -
Aditya Birla Health, Nivpa Health, Care
Health and Star Health & All. Ok? These
four companies are very big companies.  In this,
Care Health has done the highest insurance of 2425 this year.  You can see that
he has insured the lives of 2.55 crore people.
Their percentage of
claims settled within 3 months is 99.95%,
almost 100% very good performance and the
number of complaints against them is also very less.  There
is a lakh on just 17 complaints.  So I think
Care Health tops this year in the
private sector.  After that,
you can see Aditya Birla, he has insured
health insurance worth Rs 1.9 crore.
Their complaint ratio is also very low.  It
is only 12% and they have settled almost 100% claims
within 3 months.  This is also a very
good thing.  After that Nivya Bhupa
comes.  He has insured his life for Rs 1.2 crore.
Their complaint ratio per lakh
is only 18 and
they have settled 100% of their claims within 3 months.
And lastly comes Star Health
because as I said, they have 51 complaints
per lakh.  So compared to other companies,
this is definitely more.  Keep in mind that
this is also a leading company.  It
comes second in 2425.
He has insured his life for Rs 2.38 crore.  And a
little bit about the difference between general insurance
in the public sector and private sector, that
in private sector
you also get very specific insurance.  So like
ST Health or K or NIV
or Aitya B Birla will have some such
insurance which these other two companies will
not have.
They provide very specific focused insurance and you
can also get tailor-made insurance from them.  So for this, many people
prefer to appoint a
specific health insurance
specialist company for health insurance.  So, according to
me, I have explained this in a very easy and simple manner.
So these four
companies are also good.  take into consideration.
Currently, my health insurance is
with Star Health and I am not going to change it right now
because according to me, it is
not a big deal.  51 complaints per 1 lakh.
But I can definitely think about it in the future.
If the situation remains the same next year,
I may go with Care.  But
this year I am still continuing with Star.  Let me
tell you in advance that I have
no affiliation with them.
I am not his agent.  My friend is
his agent so I take the star.
Because if any problem occurs, he can
handle it personally.  This is my
personal objective.  But as I
said, if their performance goes
down a little further next year and Care or some other
company starts performing better than them, then I will
definitely think of shifting there.
So according to me this was a very simple
and work fast review for you.   If
you have any questions, please ask.
If I am available, I will definitely try to answer you.
You know I
mostly travel.  Now
next I am going for a trip to Sikkim.
So thank you so much and buy for now.